<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-10-01T15:56:44-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Theorima Film Productions</title><subtitle>Theorima Film Productions</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Irrelevance of Indistinguishability</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/indistinguishability/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Irrelevance of Indistinguishability" /><published>2024-05-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/indistinguishability</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/indistinguishability/"><![CDATA[<p>Let’s forgo the cruft and dive right into the question: Is there a fundamental difference between the artistic creations of a human and those of a machine? We can hardly finish stating the question before somebody has approached with long stride, solution in hand. Inevitably, their solution will take the form of a Turing-like test: we take some subjects, and ask them to distinguish between images (or texts, films, or what not) created by humans, and those created by machines. If our subjects are unable to meaningfully distinguish between the two then the question is settled, as no practical difference remains. There would then be no difference between AI and human art, or so the story goes.</p>

<p>It is a strange story however, stranger still in that it declares itself as a <em>solution</em> to the problem. As a solution, we should expect it to be able to <em>resolve</em> the problem, to serve as a persuasive tool. It should at least have the minimal power to change <em>some</em> minds. A solution to a question which sways neither the inclined nor disinclined has no effect, and is hardly a solution.</p>

<p>We can imagine the response to such a test as easily as we can imagine such a test being conducted. If the test failed at showing indistinguishability, those disinclined to maintain a difference would state that the test was premature, that the models used were outdated, and lacking in <em>parameters</em>. If the test succeeded, those inclined to maintain a difference would note that the test was methodologically flawed, that the artworks used were outdated, and lacking in <em>originality</em> (a poor sample of human ingenuity). 
Indeed, objections could be made regardless of how well designed the test is. It seems almost by the nature of the question that the conclusion of any test would leave an open question in the air from which an objection to the test can grow and thrive. This would not be the case for all questions of course: a regular consumer of cured salami <em>may</em> drop the habit upon seeing a well designed study linking it to cancer. But in our case, there is no conceivable scenario where the individual who maintains the difference drops it, all because of a test.</p>

<p>But the tester is unperturbed, and may take the above further if so desired: If the test was rejected by the disinclined, they must have definite reasons for doing so (sample bias, naive parametric assumptions, etc). To not have definite reasons here would be unreasonable. Given their reasons for rejection, we may run another test which addresses said issues; a test that is bigger, bolder, and hence more statistically valid. Undoubtedly, the disinclined would reject this test as well. Reasons could again be given–there is never a lack of reasons to reject a statistical test, and acceptance only indicates a will too exhausted to find faults. So again, another test, another rejection, more reasons, and so on, <em>ad infinitum</em>. “Now, wouldn’t the disinclined look a bit foolish after a while, with their constant nitpicking?” The tester could then pull out a comparison to water diviners whose beliefs, while not entirely refuted, have begun to look a bit ridiculous under the weight of growing evidence.</p>

<p>The case above bears resemblance to the man who, not sure whether fool’s gold is equivalent to real gold, runs an indistinguishability test, and upon receiving a successful result runs out into the street in his pajamas, holding bundles of pyrite and shouting: “Hoozah! They are the same, and now I am rich!” We laugh at such a person, regardless of how well his test was set up, for we know that pyrite and gold <em>are</em> different, as they differ in their <em>constitutions</em> . The test showed that they were indistinguishable. It did not show that they are the same.</p>

<p>It it likewise in our case; they are different, and they differ via their constitutions. In the case of pyrite and gold, this fact just points to another kind of test, a chemical one that reveals the molecular compositions of the objects in question. In other words, they must both be broken down in a kind of analysis, into simpler parts which can be compared so conclusions can be made. But if we were to take any artistic creation and place it under a microscope, we would not find its parts to be simpler, but to be infinitely more complex. Each part, for it to be an <strong>actual</strong> part, and not a mere abstraction, must be constituted by the same web of values, purposes, and beliefs that our simplest gestures take meaning upon. If not, then it is in some way disconnected from life, and thus exists only as a possibility, an abstraction, a figment. And so it is that within even the smallest piece of text is contained the entire world.</p>

<p>Such grandiosity may seem absurd<d-footnote>It certainly is comical.</d-footnote> to those used to taking a piece of text (or a film, a painting, etc) in the abstract, as a definite concept that may by definition be broken down into simpler parts through analysis. But when we are dealing with any creation in its full flesh and blood actuality–the way we <em>actually</em> experience it–there can be no less grandiose a conclusion. That such a mistake is common in the cases where we must take images and texts as mere “data,” is not surprising. Its in fact not even wrong to do so, as long as it is remembered that the <strong>Hamlet</strong> written by Shakespeare and embedded in culture is of a highly different nature from the <strong>Hamlet</strong> that sits encoded as ASCII in the dataset of a language model…</p>

<p>To put this testing business behind us we should finally ask: is the difference between machine art and human art something definite enough to be tested or even given a clear delineation? If we mean art in its actuality (and not as high abstraction) then this is plainly false–at least for the time being. The statement must be restricted to the present, unfortunately. A shared web of beliefs is not a static edifice. It changes little by little, day by day, resembling only dimly what is was some time ago. For the time being, art still forms a legitimate part of the world, and because of that it remains linked in the web, in touch with actuality. But values can be changed, and they can be changed in such a way that we untether art from this web, leaving it to float in the vacuum of space like a jettisoned astronaut.</p>

<p>Thus, in the end, the difference between human and machine art is something that <em>can potentially</em> be settled by a definite test, but only in the case where the role of art in life has been reduced to a nullity. By then of course, the test would say nothing. So the real question is not “is there a difference?” but “should we maintain a difference?” Whether or not there is a difference is our collective choice to make, and if we see value in this difference, it is our fight to maintain it.</p>

<hr />
<p>(Thumbnail image: Roger Bacon, conducting a scientific test. From the Middle Temple Library)</p>]]></content><author><name>Denis Claudius</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some quick notes on the irrelevance of Turing-like tests for differentiating the creations of humans and machines.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Presupposition of the Machine Culture</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/machine-culture/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Presupposition of the Machine Culture" /><published>2024-03-29T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-03-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/machine-culture</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/machine-culture/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

<p>There is a particular question that floats around the air nowadays that will soon have to be brought down with a long pole and answered: are we to draw a decisive ontological distinction between the creations of a machine, and those of a human? Or should this distinction fade into irrelevancy? The collective acceptance of AI generated art would imply the latter, its rejection the former.</p>

<p>Perhaps we could better evaluate the question by reflecting on the effects of our decision. Some implications of a collective acceptance would immediately come to mind: job loss and concomitant economic upheaval…the picture is quite clear, though those inclined to welcome this acceptance will not be moved by such notions. With a languorous gesture of the hand, they will point towards an arbitrary event in history: “Yes, and the automobile greatly reduced the need for the stableboy and crews to clean manure, but we have gotten past that, and progressed to a new and brighter era. This time is no different.”</p>

<p>While I greatly admire such unjustified optimism, unfortunately it does seem that this time is quite different. You see, behind the choice of acceptance is a presupposition, and it is this presupposition (and its consequences) that makes our situation dissimilar from those of the past. But before we discuss this presupposition, we must unfortunately theorize about art.</p>

<h2 id="the-mechanical-and-the-existential">The Mechanical and the Existential</h2>
<div class="row mt-1">
    <div class="col-sm mt-1 mt-md-0">
	

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
      <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/joan2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/joan2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/joan2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp" />
    
    <img src="/assets/img/joan2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
    <figcaption class="caption">A close-up from "The Passion of Joan of Arc".</figcaption>
  
</figure>

    </div>
</div>

<p>What constitutes a work of art? Well, I’m not entirely sure; a work of art is not like a pie, with a set of clearly delineated ingredients transmuted to make a whole. To make the task slightly easier, let’s take a single example: what constitutes the film <strong><em>The Passion of Joan of Arc</em></strong>?</p>

<p>One aspect that can be seen immediately is its formal properties: the iconic close-ups, the low angle shots of harrowing churchmen, the precise movements of the camera; these are the kinds of elements that are revealed directly on the surface. If, say, an alien were to arrive, with no knowledge of the relations of human life, these would be perhaps the only elements we could discuss with them. We could point to the screen: “You see? That is a closeup, see how it is used at such and such a place…” Of course, they would not understand <strong><em>why</em></strong> these formal elements are being used, but they will at least know that they <em>are</em> being used. Perhaps, after decades of watching Dreyer’s films on repeat, we could give our alien a camera, a crew, some cash, and send them out to make a film of their own. The resulting movie will likely have many of the same formal elements, but nevertheless something will be missing from it all, giving the overall film an air of strangeness…We may suggestively call these formal elements the <strong><em>mechanical elements</em></strong>, as they are the only elements of the work which could in principle be reproduced or understood systematically/mechanically.</p>

<p>But after we have exhausted the mechanical, what else is left? Everything that is <strong><em>not</em></strong> mechanical, and thus sundry, nebulous, and hard to describe. These are the elements which we could not teach the alien, because they are not derived from the surface, but instead have their basis in the fact that the work was created, and is appreciated by, some <em>someone</em> who <strong><em>exists</em></strong>, someone who holds subjective experience in a world shared with others. The faith of Joan, the cruelty of the churchmen, the purpose and meaning <em>behind</em> the close-ups and low angles, these cannot be understood without some reference to a subjective existence, and the backdrop of the world upon which it takes meaning.<d-footnote>Cf. Wittgenstein, Culture and Value</d-footnote> We would need to take the alien out of the theatre and into the world to understand these elements. How could the close-ups even be understood without reference to Joan’s passion, the very title of the movie? How could this passion be understood without understanding the vague desire to be subsumed by something great and unknowable? And how could this vague desire be understood without reference to existence in a shared world?</p>

<p>These kinds of elements of a work cannot survive without reference to subjectivity, that is, to existence. To deny the privilege to reference it is to deny all elements of a work of art, with the exception of the mechanical. We may suggestively call these non mechanical elements of a work its <strong><em>existential</em></strong> elements, as it is the only aspect of a work of art that requires a relationship with subjectivity, without which it dissipates into nothing.</p>

<h2 id="relating-the-mechanical-and-the-existential">Relating the Mechanical and the Existential</h2>

<p>Both aspects, the mechanical and the existential play their role in making a work what it is; neither should be given undue prominence over the other. The mechanical does what the formal is expected to do; these are the definite elements of the work, and they serve to give shape and coherence to the indefinite, the existential, elements which lie beneath the surface. The existential elements, on the other hand, are the points of contact between art and life. Being the only elements with a relationship to existence, it is only through these elements that life, whether it be the experience of an individual or a city or a nation, can seep through and actively affect the creation and reception of a work.</p>

<p>But what good is this? Why does art need the grubby fingerprints of life smeared across it? The reason is simple: because life is the only known source of novelty, and so if there is to be anything truly new in a work, it must have its basis in life, in existence. There may be novelty in the mechanical elements of course (just think of Dreyer’s novel use of the close-up), but formal novelty is always derived from and in service of the existential (because Dreyer used the close-ups <em>for a reason</em>). We may suggestively say then, that the mechanical elements are the engines of order, while the existential elements are the engines of novelty.</p>

<h2 id="a-presupposition">A Presupposition</h2>

<p>Now let’s return to where we started. There is a presupposition in the collective acceptance of AI art, but what is it? Our ponderous journey above makes this easy to state: it presupposes the wholesale denial of the existential elements in a work of art. The very notion of “AI art” is paradoxical as long as the existential remains a factor, and for this reason it must be denied. This denial may come in the form either of asserting that the existential may be done away with, or that it had never existed as a factor at the start. Either way, the acceptance of AI art and the existential are mutually exclusive notions. They represent the two sides of the choice referenced at the beginning–<em>choice</em> is what it ultimately comes down to. The acceptance or rejection of the existential is not a matter to be resolved with mathematical argument or statistical analysis; that is the domain of the mechanical. It is the domain of individual to choose or reject the existential. Their decision is at the same time a choice about their vision for humanity, and as such, has consequences that resonate throughout all aspects of life…</p>

<h2 id="the-machine-culture">The Machine Culture</h2>

<p>The relationship between art and life is best described as a cycle: life gives breath to art, and art provides ideals to life, creating new reasons to create…and so on. It is a propagating activity, and to a culture almost as basic as the electromagnetic wave. Once the existential has been purged, this cycle will be severed, and life will have no avenues left to influence artistic creation of any kind. How can it, if all the elements that relate to life are gone? Art will be constituted solely of the mechanical. And though it would no longer reflect life, I don’t think its unreasonable to assume that art would still be reflected <em>in</em> life. But life which reflects mechanical art cannot help but be mechanical. It would be a new culture, different in kind and not just degree, one that could aptly be called a “machine culture.” It would be culture entirely populated by the “machine men, with machine minds, and machine hearts”<d-footnote>It should be noted that the machine-man is not necessarily endemic to the machine culture; many such machine-men can be found wandering about the culture even now...</d-footnote> of Chaplin’s speech.</p>

<p>Cut from life and unable to create novelty, a machine culture does nothing but reproduce statements within its own precisely defined system.<d-footnote>An interesting point may be brought up that this would be the first time in history where a system of life could be said to be entirely owned and operated by a handful of individuals.</d-footnote> The system can be changed of course, new models may be trained, more data may be tabulated–but the system can never be broken out of. Some may point out that we already, in some sense, live in a machine culture. This is correct to a degree. Day by day, larger and larger portions of the broader culture are being created according to strict systematic processes. However, even the most cynical works, inspired by Excel spreadsheets and driven by the board, have the faintest amount of the existential. They can still react and take influence from life, even if this reaction is facile and disingenuous. It would not be so in the machine culture. So, yes, the machine culture is close-by, but it is not here yet and it is by no means inevitable. It is only inevitable if it is accepted as inevitable.</p>]]></content><author><name>Denis Claudius</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A brief overview of a key presupposition regarding the notion of AI art]]></summary></entry></feed>